hi everyone today I'll be talking about
support vector machines you can find all
my sample Python code on github
a dash of data first I'll go through
some SVM basics starting with a visual
introduction and then a step-by-step
walkthrough some sample code in Python
and then I'll talk about how you can
fine tune your model with some
additional complexities and then I'll
give you my final thoughts on SVM so
let's start with what is a support
vector machine well it's a
classification technique so what does
that mean so let's say we had all these
blue dots and all these teal desks and I
asked you to classify this data so
another way to say that is if I had
asked you to split the data well what
would you do you could split the data
this way or this way or this way all of
those ways work but what if I asked you
to split the data in the best possible
way well then you probably say that this
line best splits that data so at the end
of the day that's essentially what a
support vector machine is it's this
model that best splits this blue and
teal sections so why is this the best
flip well let's say that that line in
the middle there that that's the meeting
of the road and that these are the two
lanes of the road so in this case this
is the widest roads that separates these
two groups so if we go back and look at
some of those other lines that we had
used to split the data you can see that
they create some pretty narrow roads but
this one here this is the widest road
that separates the two groups look at in
some more technical terms now so instead
of saying this is the widest road that
separates the two groups we can say that
this is the widest margin that separates
the two groups another way to say this
is the distance between the points and
this line are as far as possible so
again these points here these can also
be called support vectors
and this line here this can be called
the hyperplane okay so those are all our
technical terms so let's summarize all
this again if I had asked you to split
this data in the best way possible we
can now say that this is the hyperplane
that best splits the data because it's
as far as possible from these support
vectors here which is another way of
saying we have maximized the margin okay
so how do you maximize the margin well
this is actually a constrained
optimization problem so there's two
parts there is a constraint and the
optimization piece let's break it down
the reason that you're trying to
optimize something is because in this
case we're trying to maximize the margin
and the reason that there are
constraints is because our constraint
here is that being staff here they can't
be on the road they have to be away from
the road so we have our constraints and
we have our optimization so this is a
constrained optimization problem the way
to solve a constrained optimization
problem is to use Lagrange multipliers
which involve quite a bit more math so
I'm not going to go through it here in
detail but now we've covered the basics
visually of how SVM works so now what
well let's apply this to a real-world
problem so my other passion in life
second to data science just a 2-second
to data science is baking so these are
all things that I've baked in the past
and the one I wanted to focus on here
are these cupcakes so every time that I
make cupcakes
my husband I always have this debate on
cupcakes versus muffins
he thinks that they're exactly the same
thing except that cupcake just has
frosting and a muffin has random
business stuff in it so being the
experience bigger than I am I completely
disagree and I just know that cupcakes
and muffins are inherently different
like they're batter is different and so
I decided to challenge myself and create
a classifier to classify recipes as
cupcakes or muffins so that way once
I've built my model
when I give my model a new recipe it
should automatically predict whether
that recipe is a cupcake recipe or a
muffin recipe so there are three steps I
need to take to do this first I need to
find the data then I'll apply a data
science model which in this case will be
SEM and then finally I'll review the
results so first let's find that data
all the way I did this was I went to
Google and I googled basic math and
recipe and basic cupcake recipe and I
recorded the top ten muffin and top ten
cupcake recipes so surprisingly muffins
and cupcakes just has eight ingredients
in them and then also surprisingly with
all twenty recipes were different there
were no duplicates in there but then as
I started looking into this data I
noticed that there were some problems my
main problem was that each recipe
yielded a different amount of batter so
one cupcake recipe might have had one
cup of flour another cupcake recipe
would have four cups of flour and
because those always were so different
if I were to put that data straight into
my model it would actually see those two
recipes as being completely different
even though they were both cupcakes so I
realized the first thing I had to do was
normalize my data and the way I did this
was I took my data from being amount
based so for instance here we have
lesson 1 having 2 cups of flour 1/2 cup
of sugar and so on 2 percent base so
black and one is 47 percent flour 24
percent sugar and so on and so at the
end of the day this is what my data look
like you can see for every row I've
labeled it as a muffin or cupcake and
then I have all my ingredients here and
each row adds up to 100% all right I
found my data so the next step is to
apply a data science model so to do this
I wrote a python script and Jupiter
notebook so I followed six steps here
and I'll go through each of them in
detail first is to import library
so I imported libraries for
analysis you can see pandas numpy and
scikit-learn and then I imported another
couple libraries for visuals so we have
math live here and then see one to make
things beautiful the next thing I did
was I imported my data so from my pandas
library I use the read dot CSV function
and you can see that the data looks
pretty good here and then before I set
my model what I always like to do is
visualize the data to see if it makes
sense so I find that out of the eight
ingredients I wanted to plot two of
those ingredients so in this case I
chose sugar and butter because I baked
for a long time and I just had a feeling
that those two ingredients would be most
likely to differentiate my cupcakes and
so when I created the scatter plot here
you can see I was right those muffins
are on the bottom left there and they
have very little sugar and very little
butter
whereas cupcakes have a ton of sugar a
ton of butter and so when you look at
this you can see it's actually a pretty
good candidate for SCM so the next I'm
going to do is fit the model so we had
talked about sugar and butter before so
I'm going to use those two ingredients
as inputs from a model and then I'm also
going to input all the labels so that
one column as you saw before that had
all the muffins and cupcakes labels and
then I'm going to put the mental model
here so you can see that I'm using SB m
dot @ CC so what s EC stands for is
support vector classifier so there's
also SBR which is for regressions the
best not use as commonly but you need to
specify SVC for classification which is
what support vectors are typically used
for and then also here you see that I
set the kernel equal to linear I'm going
to talk about kernel a little bit more
later on the presentation but just one
to let you know that for the basic case
you want to set kernel equal
here and then you can fit your model and
on the bottom there you can see our
output so that output doesn't mean much
so let's visualize it okay so the
visualization steps are actually quite
lengthy I'm going to go through them
quickly but you can review the code in
detail on github so here I created a
hyper plane along with the dotted lines
for the margins and I'm plotting all of
that on to a plot that you see here so
on the left you can see that this is our
X fan model and on the right you can see
that we've maximized the margin all
right so now I've applied a data science
model so the next step is to review the
results see if they make sense so just
to reiterate the challenge was to
classify recipes as cupcakes or muffins
and when given a new recipe determine if
it's a cupcake or a muffin recipe so
let's go back to our code so what I've
done here is I've applauded one
additional point that you'll apply right
there and that's a new recipe and so
visually you can tell that that recipe
is supposed to be a muffin because with
all those bright dots but we want our
model to predict that automatically so
let's see if I model can do that so here
i've created a function called
muffin or cupcake and what we need to do
is input the amount of butter and sugar
that that recipe has and then I'll tell
you the answer there down here I put in
my new recipe that has 12 parts butter
and 12 part sugar and it tells us that
we are looking at a muffin which is
correct based on the visual on last
slide so at the end of the day we see
that muffins and cupcakes are not the
same thing but they're actually
different and you can classify them
using support vector machine so I want
that argument all right
so that was our basic case so let's talk
about how to make SVM even more powerful
so there are four things that I wanted
to go through in this additional
complexity section starting with higher
dimensions so for the last bit of slides
we've been working with two dimensions
sugar and butter and we were able to
separate that using a line so let's say
we wanted to add another dimension so
let's say flour and we would have three
dimensions and we could separate that
data with a plane let's say we had four
dimensions in that case we'd separate
our data with a hyperplane but it gets
pretty hard to visualize so here's the
cool thing even though it's hard to
visualize it's actually very easy to
code so here is our original code and we
were putting in the butter and sugar
ingredients you can see that data right
there so let's say we didn't want to
just get two dimensions but we wanted to
get all eight ingredients well all we
have to do is input all eight
ingredients here and the code will
automatically take this information and
run the models and so the reason that we
want to add in more dimensions is
because with more dimensions there's the
opportunity to further maximize that
margin and create a better model okay
moving on to C parameter so on the left
here you can see this is the data that
we've been working with and we were able
to separate it with a line pretty easily
but I actually hid one piece of data
from you so this is what the original
data actually looked like and you can
tell there's this red dot on the top of
the screen there and if we were to
create that line on the left you see
that that red actually gets
misclassified so this is where the C
parameter comes in so the C parameter
allowed you to decide how much you want
to penalize is misclassified points if
you look at our original code again you
can see the C parameter was hiding in
our output here
so the default value for the C parameter
is 1 but you can vary it so here are
some visuals to helps but understand
this so on the left here I've given the
SVM model a low C value 2 to the
negative fifth and on the right a high
of C value 2 to the fifth and so you can
see the difference in the two models
here on the left the model just allows
that point to be in the classified and
on the right there's known the
classification so on the left here with
a low C parameter we are prioritizing
simplicity so this line here is also
called
a line with a soft margin because we're
allowing that miss classification on the
right here we're prioritizing making a
few mistakes as possible so there is few
mistakes here but in this case we're
probably overfitting because this model
is just so close to all those blue
points if you were to bring in a new
recipe in the future it might actually
classify that incorrectly so how do you
pick the best C parameter well what you
need to do is try different values see
all the way from let's say 2 to negative
fist to 2 to the positive fist and then
see what the best C value is for your
model all right
let's also talk about multiple classes
so one cool thing about SPMS is it
doesn't just classify two classes it's
also able to classify more than two
classes so in this case I've added some
green dots here and these are your
skills so this is what it's going with
Clyde clickers that don't know and with
SVM you can actually classify your data
into three different groups here so on
the Left we have our muffins in red we
have our cupcakes and the right we have
our green stuff so how can you do that
in the code very easily so all you need
to do is add
a parameter called decision function
sheet and you can set it equal to OB r
or ovo so what are those ways so OB R
means one versus rest so what it does is
if you had let's say here he had three
different groups that you want to
classify what OVR would do is it would
try its best to classify the blue group
versus all the rest of the data create
that hyperplane and then it would try to
separate the red group from the rest of
the data and then the remaining data it
was put into the green group on the
other hand its ovo so it will compare
all the classes separately and create a
hyperplane for each one of them and then
combine all that information so there's
some pros and cons to both here so the
pro to the OVR approach is that there
are fewer classifications that need to
be made so let's say we were actually
classifying ten different groups well in
that case we would have to create nine
different models so we create a model
for one versus rest for every single
class and then for that tenth class
that's just where the remaining data
goes and then for the ovo technique if
you were to classify every class against
the other with ten different classes
there it's actually a combination of 10
ticks 2 which is 45 different
classifications it takes a very long
time with the pro to the ovo technique
is that it's less sensitive ten balanced
so let's look at the left side there the
OVR side so if you were to classify the
blue group versus say nine other groups
that blue group is really small the nine
other groups might just overpower that
pieces and to say that nothing is part
of that blue class so that's a bit of
imbalance right there whereas on the ovo
side that won't happen as much could use
comparing one class at a time so it's
really up to you what technique you want
all right finally I want to talk about
the kernel trick
so no SVM presentation is complete
without the kernel trick so let's say
that we had this data on the left here
we have red dots and some blue dots and
I asked you to draw a hyperplane to
separate that data could you do it
you'll probably try to draw a line like
this and that doesn't work well we're
still able to separate this data with
SVM by using the kernel trick so the
curl trick does is think of it as adding
another dimension to this data so what
this contract does in this case you see
it's taken that data on the left and
added a dimension of Z dimension so that
you can now linearly separate that data
with a hyperplane okay so there are a
couple different kernel options in
Python there's a linear kernel radial
basis function
RBF polynomial sigmoid so I want to say
here you can see that even though you
weren't able to separate with a line in
two dimensions that using that kernel
trick if you project that track on the
right into 2d you can see that it
becomes that graph on the left okay so
what does this look like in the code
well our original code our kernel was
set to be linear but in our updated code
here you can see I've set kernel equal
to RBF so that's a really popular one to
try out and with RBF you need to set two
additional parameters so it's C
parameter and a gamma parameter so we
talked a little bit about C already but
now I want to talk more about gamma so
on the left here you have just our basic
linear kernel and I've set C equal to
one and then for the right to graph
those are two more graphs with RBF at
the kernel and these still equals one
but I
very the gamaheer so I buried it from to
the negative 5th all the ways a to data
first and immediately you can see the
difference between the two gamma values
so with a small gamma value there's less
complexity it's kind of a small p-value
here you're seeing it's allowing those
misclassifications and on the right you
see a bit large camera where we're
overfitting big time so it's pretty much
classifying everything as a cupcake
which at the end of the day if you're
eating muffins scones or cupcakes you
are essentially just eating a cupcake
but you can see here that it's actually
not a good model so you probably want
this lower gamma in this table but how
do you choose the best gamma well we're
going to have to try a bunch of
different C and gamma combinations using
grid search and see which one is best
for your data all right so that's all I
had for SBN I wanted to also just
mention when you should use Assam's so
about the pros there are a couple pros
the best fans one is that it's good at
dealing with high dimensional data so
you saw with a carl trick that it's able
to use high dimensions effectively also
it works well on small datasets so in
our case here we just had 20 different
recipes that we were looking at the
pretty small data set and as sample is
able to classify that data very well the
main con is that picking the right
kernel and then also the right
parameters can be very difficult and
computationally intensive so if you were
you're having to run this Sam model on
10 different speed parameters gamma
parameters that would just take a long
time and probably not the most effective
way to hold a classification model so in
that case there are some other
classification techniques you can use
that I've listed here and there's no set
way of figuring out which
his best my advice to you would be just
to try multiple techniques on your data
set and see which one works the best on
your data all right that's all I have on
support vector machines again you can
find sample Python code on github
- of data thanks